Guide to the Cedric J. Robinson and Elizabeth P. Robinson Collection on Third World News Review TAM.835
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- Series II: Third World News Review Episodes, 1981-2015; 1.67 Linear Feet in 2 manuscript boxes and a cassette box; 1.79 Terabytes in 496 computer files; 3 U-matic; 15 VHS; 29 audiocassettes
  - March 31, 2003, TW_TAM_835_ER_16
    The moderator of the episode was Cedric Robinson and the guests were Elizabeth Robinson and Phoebe Hirsch-Dubin (Mexico). Discussed topics include the Iraq War and human rights violations of Iraqi prisoners; the meeting of the International Atomic Energy Agency in Vienna; and a discussion of the United States' allies in Latin American countries (Colombia, Bolivia, and El Salvador) versus those opposed to the United States (Triple Frontier -- Paraguay, Brazil and Argentina).
  - April 7, 2003, TW_TAM_835_ER_17
    The moderator of the episode was Cedric Robinson and the guests were Elizabeth Robinson and Katia McClain. Discussed topics include the Iraq War; the Battle of Jenin in Israel and the shooting of American activist Brian Avery by the Israeli Defense Forces; the reconstruction of Afghanistan; the Bush Administration cutting veteran's benefits; and the assassination of Zoran Đinđić.
  - April 14, 2003, TW_TAM_835_ER_18
    The moderator of the episode was Elizabeth Robinson and the guests were Cedric Robinson and Gerard Pigeon. Topics discussed include the Iraq War; anti-war movements in the United States and globally; the removal of Saddam Hussein's statue in Baghdad; and the destruction of the Antiquity Museum in Baghdad, libraries, and other cultural heritage sites.
  - April 21, 2003
    The moderator of the episode was Cedric Robinson and the guests were Elizabeth Robinson, Will Thomas (Middle East), and Paul Lynch (Middle East). Discussed topics include the Iraq War and anti-war protests globally; destruction and looting of cultural heritage sites in Baghdad; efforts made towards preserving Iraqi oil fields; ongoing conflict between Israel and Palestine in the Gaza Strip; and the death of Rachel Corrie in Rafah, Gaza Strip.
    - Audio (Box 4, Audiocassette 835_0003)
    - Digital Video Recording, TW_TAM_835_ER_19
  - April 28, 2003, TW_TAM_835_ER_20
    The moderator of the episode was Cedric Robinson and the guests were Katia McClain and Elizabeth Robinson. Discussed topics include Romania and Bulgaria's bid to join the EU; the Iraq War; the Bosnian War; increased salaries and budgets of U.S. defense contractors; and the negative impact of globalization on small rural communities in India and protests against globalization in Hyderabad.
  - May 5, 2003, TW_TAM_835_ER_21
    The moderator of the episode was Cedric Robinson and the guests were Gerard Pigeon and Elizabeth Robinson. Discussed topics include the Iraq War; British elections and lack of support for Tony Blair; continued violence in the Gaza Strip; the death of Rachel Corrie in Rafah, Gaza Strip and the attack against Brian Avery; the First Ivorian Civil War and the signing of UN Intervention ceasefire accords; and civil wars in Liberia and Sierra Leone.
  - May 12, 2003, TW_TAM_835_ER_22
    The moderator of the episode was Cedric Robinson and the guests were Gerard Pigeon and Elizabeth Robinson. Discussed topics include the Jayson Blair scandal; protests against Halliburton; Barbara Bodine, her time at UCSB, and her affiliation with the invasion of Iraq; PFC Jessica Lynch; the civil war in Sierra Leone; peace in Liberia and Ivory Coast; and the ongoing conflict between Israel and Palestine.
  - May 19, 2003, TW_TAM_835_ER_23
    The moderator of the episode was Cedric Robinson and the guests were Katia McClain and Elizabeth Robinson. Discussed topics include the Iraq War, discrimination facing Roma communities in Eastern Europe, vandalism of historical structures in Iraq by American soldiers, the United Nations Human Rights Commission discussing the destruction in Gaza, the first hearings of Sierra Leone's Truth and Reconciliation Commission, and the civil war in Liberia.
  - June 2, 2003, TW_TAM_835_ER_24
    The moderator of the episode was Elizabeth Robinson and the guests were Gerard Pigeon, Ralph Ambruster-Sandoval, and Cedric Robinson. Discussed topics include the Bogoro massacre in the Democratic Republic of the Congo; the end of Sierra Leone's civil war and creation of a Truth and Reconciliation Commission; corruption of Liberian president President Charles Taylor; the Iraq War; the 29th G8 Summit; and the growing number of femicides in Ciudad Juárez, Mexico.
  - June 9, 2003, TW_TAM_835_ER_25
    The moderator of the episode was Cedric Robinson and the guests were Gerard Pigeon and Elizabeth Robinson. Discussed topics include the Iraq War, Guantanamo Bay prison, Osama bin Laden, and Saddam Hussein; the 2003 Central African Republic coup d'état; discussion of discrepancies in media depictions of Palestinian support for Yasser Arafat; and sanctions against President Charles Taylor by the United Nations Security Council.
  - June 16, 2003, TW_TAM_835_ER_26
    The moderator of the episode was Cedric Robinson and the guests were H.L.T (HQ) Quan (Asia) and Elizabeth Robinson. Discussed topics include the 36th Annual Association of Southeast Asian Nations (ASEAN) and the ASEAN Free Trade Area (AFTA); the Iraq War; the attempted assassination of Aung San Suu Kyi; protests in Indonesia against the Union Oil Company of California (Unocal); and global terrorism.
  - June 23, 2003, TW_TAM_835_ER_27
    Moderator and Guests: None
    This was a special episode focusing on a lecture given by Vandana Shiva at UCSB titled "Resource Monopolies versus Truth Democracy" on March 4, 2003. Topics discussed include globalization, international trade, and the General Agreement on Trade Tariffs (GATT); pharmaceutical and biotechnology industries; and India.
  - June 30, 2003, TW_TAM_835_ER_28
    The moderator of the episode was Cedric Robinson and the guests were Hector Javkin and Katia McClain. Discussed topics include the Pope's visit to the Balkans; the Bosnian War and the Dayton Accords; the European Union-Western Balkans Summit; the European Union and International Criminal Court; Albania's bid to join NATO; the Iraq War; the trial of President Slobodan Milošević; the extradition and trial of Ricardo Camacho; and the indictment of President Charles Taylor.
  - July 7, 2003, TW_TAM_835_ER_29
    The moderator of the episode was Cedric Robinson and the guests were Elizabeth Robinson and Katia McClain. Discussed topics include oil production in Africa, the Extractive Industries Transparency Initiative, and political instability in Nigeria; the Iraq War; the ongoing conflicts between Israel and Palestine; and the roles and responsibilities of the United Nations Security Council and the International Criminal Court.
  - July 14, 2003, TW_TAM_835_ER_30
    The moderator of the episode was Cedric Robinson and the guests were Gary Colmenar and Elizabeth Robinson. Discussed topics include the Iraq War; Iranian filmmaker Abbas Kiarostami and his latest film, Ten; the history of American imperialism in the Philippines; and President George W. Bush's trip to Senegal.
  - July 21, 2003, TW_TAM_835_ER_31
    The moderator of the episode was Katia McClain and the guests were Gerard Pigeon and Hector Javkin. Discussed topics include President George W. Bush's trip to Africa; peace talks between the Colombian government and paramilitary groups; the history of Argentina's government under Isabel Perón, Carlos Menem, and Cristina Fernández de Kirchner; and the Iraq War.
  - July 30, 2003, TW_TAM_835_ER_32
    The moderator of the episode was Elizabeth Robinson and the guests were Lisa Hajjar (Middle East) and Cedric Robinson. Discussed topics include the history of Liberia and former Liberian president, President Charles Taylor; the legal system in Sierra Leone; Israel-U.S. relations, the West Bank Barrier, and Gaza; and the wars in Iraq and Afghanistan.
  - August 4, 2003, TW_TAM_835_ER_33
    The moderator of the episode was Cedric Robinson and the guests were Hector Javkin and Elizabeth Robinson. Discussed topics include the Iraq War; Israel's plans for a West Bank wall; Apartheid in South Africa; the Argentinian economy and growing unemployment; the signing of a free trade agreement between the U.S. and Chile; a Chilean court investigating human rights abuses; and the indictment of President Charles Taylor.
  - August 11, 2003, TW_TAM_835_ER_34
    The moderator of the episode was Cedric Robinson and the guests were Gerard Pigeon and Elizabeth Robinson. Discussed topics include transition of power in Liberia between President Charles Taylor and Vice President Mosese Blah; the indictment of President Charles Taylor and his political asylum in Nigeria; the intersection of activism and agricultural rights in the fight against globalization; the War in Afghanistan; and the history of U.S. foreign policy regarding the Middle East.
  - August 18, 2003, TW_TAM_835_ER_35
    The moderator of the episode was Cedric Robinson and the guests were Katia McClain and Elizabeth Robinson. Discussed topics include the signing of a peace accord and the ending of violence in Liberia; attempts to remove Carla Del Ponte as a UN War Crimes Prosecutor and the difficulties in prosecuting war crimes; violence in Kosovo; controversy surrounding a Mother Teresa sculpture in Macedonia; and Libya agreeing to pay reparations to those impacted by the Lockerbie airplane affair.
  - August 25, 2003, TW_TAM_835_ER_36
    The moderator of the episode was Cedric Robinson and the guests were Thomas Jacob and Hector Javkin. Discussed topics include attempts to overturn amnesty laws in Argentina; the Iraq War; bombings in Mumbai; growing religious tensions and fundamentalism in India; and the Rwandan elections.
  - September 8, 2003, TW_TAM_835_ER_37
    The moderator of the episode was Cedric Robinson and the guests were Gerard Pigeon and Elizabeth Robinson. Discussed topics include the Iraq War; ongoing tensions between Presidents Yasser Arafat and Mahmoud Abbas leading to Abbas' resignation; the ongoing conflict in Gaza and a report by the Norwegian Refugee Council documenting human rights violations in Palestine; and political instability leading to violence in Liberia and the Ivory Coast.
  - September 15, 2003, TW_TAM_835_ER_38
    The moderator of the episode was Cedric Robinson and the guests were Hector Javkin and Elizabeth Robinson. Discussed topics include the Iraq War, a coup d'etat in Guinea-Bissau, post-Civil War reconciliation in Liberia, the Israeli government's decision to remove President Yasser Arafat from the West Bank, collapse of the World Trade Organization meeting in Cancun, and the ongoing conflict between Palestine and Israel.
  - September 22, 2003, TW_TAM_835_ER_39
    The moderator of the episode was Cedric Robinson and the guests were Katia McClain and Gerard Pigeon. Discussed topics include the history of TWNR and two retrospective topics - Nicaragua accusing the United States of mining their harbors in 1984 and the Iranian hostage crisis; reconciliation between Croatia and Serbia over war atrocities; the Iraq War; ongoing conflicts between Israel and Palestine; a resurgence of antisemitism in France; and civil and political unrest in Ivory Coast.
  - September 29, 2003, TW_TAM_835_ER_40
    The moderator of the episode was Cedric Robinson and the guests were Katia McClain and Elizabeth Robinson. Discussed topics include the death of Edward Said; the Iraq War and the War in Afghanistan; intelligence scandal involving Joseph Wilson, Valerie Palm, and the CIA; President Charles Taylor and his political asylum in Nigeria; the United States' refusal to join the International Criminal Court; and the Srebrenica massacre.
  - October 6, 2003, TW_TAM_835_ER_41
    The moderator of the episode was Elizabeth Robinson and the guests were Hector Javkin and Lisa Hajjar (Middle East). Discussed topics include the ongoing conflict between Israel and Palestine in the West Bank and Gaza; Hamas, the Islamic Jihad, and their opposition to President Yasser Arafat; the Iraq War; the International Monetary Fund and Argentina's debt crisis; and fighting in Colombia between the national government and revolutionary groups.
  - October 13, 2003, TW_TAM_835_ER_42
    The moderator of the episode was Cedric Robinson and the guests were Gerard Pigeon and Elizabeth Robinson. Discussed topics include Israel's infiltration of Rafah; concerns over Iran's nuclear capabilities and the UN International Atomic Energy Agency's deadline for a full inspection; discussion of countries with nuclear programs; the Iraq War and search for Saddam Hussein; upcoming French election and fears of a recession; and Mumia Abu-Jamal and Angela Davis.
  - October 20, 2003, TW_TAM_835_ER_43
    The moderator of the episode was Elizabeth Robinson and the guests were Gary Colmenar, Hector Javkin, and Cedric Robinson. Discussed topics include demonstrations related to resignation of Bolivian president Gonzalo Sanchez Losada; the ex-NYT journalist Jayson Blair scandal; the Free Trade Area of the Americas agreement; war in the Democratic Republic of the Congo; President George W. Bush's visit to the Philippines; and the growing rate of poverty in the Philippines.
  - October 27, 2003, TW_TAM_835_ER_44
    The moderator of the episode was Elizabeth Robinson and the guests were Gerard Pigeon and Katia McClain. Discussed topics include the Bulgarian elections and the rise of socialism; controversial elections in Chechnya and Azerbaijan; the United Nations' anti-landmine campaign; controversies about US military bases in Central Asia; the Iraq War; and tensions between French and Ivory Coast governments over funding.
  - November 3, 2003, TW_TAM_835_ER_45
    The moderator of the episode was Cedric Robinson and the guests were Hector Javkin and Elizabeth Robinson. Discussed topics include the Iraq War; the assassination of Yitzhak Rabin; the ongoing conflict between Israel and Palestine; the forced resignation of six British police officers over allegations of racism and corruption; the decline in protests after Carlos Mesa became president of Bolivia; Chile signing a free trade pact with the U.S.; Argentina continuing to prosecute generals involved in the "Dirty War"; and the indictment of President Charles Taylor.
  - November 17, 2003, TW_TAM_835_ER_46
    The moderator of the episode was Cedric Robinson and the guests were Katia McClain and Gerard Pigeon. Discussed topics include the Iraq War, President George W. Bush's visit to the U.K., the human trafficking problem in Albania, the controversial elections in Georgia, the failed election in Serbia, the Okinawan government's request to remove all American troops, and the European Social Forum meeting in Paris.
  - November 24, 2003, TW_TAM_835_ER_47
    The moderator of the episode was Elizabeth Robinson and the guests were Phoebe Hirsch-Dubin (Mexico), Katia McClain, and Hector Javkin. Discussed topics include the Free Trade Agreement of the Americas (FTA), the Iraq War, controversial elections in Georgia, a fire at Patrice Lumumba College in Moscow, a lecture by Rigoberta Menchu Tum at UCSB, and the anniversary of the founding of the Zapatista Army of National Liberation (EZLN).
  - December 1, 2003, TW_TAM_835_ER_48
    The moderator of the episode was Cedric Robinson and the guests were Gerard Pigeon and Elizabeth Robinson. Discussed topics include President Charles Taylor seeking political asylum in Nigeria and the ongoing civil war in Liberia; trial of former members of the security forces in South Africa who conspired to kill President Nelson Mandela; instability in Ivory Coast; mortality rates globally due to HIV/AIDS; issues surrounding abortions in the U.S. and globally; the release of some British and American prisoners from Guantanamo Bay; and the Iraq War.
  - December 8, 2003, TW_TAM_835_ER_49
    The moderator of the episode was Cedric Robinson and the guests were Gerard Pigeon and Hector Javkin. Discussed topics include declassified documents linking Henry Kissinger and Argentina; the International Monetary Fund and Argentina's debt crisis; the Iraq War; fighting in Ivory Coast with the French and increased xenophobia; criticism about Liberia's interim government; and scandal surrounding President Charles Taylor.
  - December 15, 2003, TW_TAM_835_ER_50
    The moderator of the episode was Cedric Robinson and the guests were Lisa Hajjar (Middle East) and Gary Colmenar. Discussed topics include the tribunal of Saddam Hussein, protests related to growing labor unrest in South Korea, the Filipino elections, attempts at demobilizing government troops in Liberia, a sex scandal linked to the Liberian government, and Halliburton illegally overcharging the Department of Defense for gasoline delivered to Iraq.
  - December 22, 2003, TW_TAM_835_ER_51
    The moderator of the episode was Cedric Robinson and the guests were Elizabeth Robinson, H.L.T (HQ) Quan (Asia), and Gerard Pigeon. Discussed topics include the Iraq War and the capture of Saddam Hussein; Islamophobia in the U.S.; the reconstruction of Iraq; ongoing conflicts in Gaza and the West Bank; the upcoming Taiwanese elections; concerns about North Korea's nuclear weapons program; and religious clothing ban in French schools.
  - January 5, 2004, TW_TAM_835_ER_52
    The moderator of the episode was Cedric Robinson and the guests were Katia McClain and Elizabeth Robinson. Discussed topics include fear of terrorism and increased security at American airports; political scandals and parliamentary opposition to the National Rainbow Coalition in Kenya; the indictment of President Charles Taylor by the International Criminal Court; the Iraq War; the Socialist Party winning the Bulgarian election; political and socio-economic instability in the Balkans; U.S. imposed sanctions on Libya; and the ongoing conflict between Israel and Palestine.
  - January 12, 2004, TW_TAM_835_ER_53
    The moderator of the episode was Cedric Robinson and the guests were Gerard Pigeon and Hector Javkin. Discussed topics include an increased number of progressive governments in Latin America; a meeting in Mexico to discuss free trade agreements in Latin America; attempts to rebuild Iraq; a coup in Haiti and President Jean-Bertrand Aristide; and the discharge of three American military personnel over allegations of abusing Iraqi prisoners.
  - January 26, 2004, TW_TAM_835_ER_54
    The moderator of the episode was Cedric Robinson and the guests were Gerard Pigeon and Elizabeth Robinson. Discussed topics include the indictment of former Liberian president Charles Taylor and problems with the interim Liberian government; protests in Europe and the Middle East over the French government's ban on Muslim head scarves; the rise of antisemitism in France; the Iraq War; the death of David Christopher Kelly; the ongoing conflict between Israel and Palestine; and the life and legacy of Jean Léopold Dominique.
  - February 2, 2004, TW_TAM_835_ER_55
    The moderator of the episode was Cedric Robinson and the guests were Hector Javkin and Elizabeth Robinson. Discussed topics include the construction of Israel's West Bank wall, continued fighting in Gaza, and Israel's deteriorating economy; the Hutton Inquiry and death of David Christopher Kelly; the Iraq War; land row dilemma for Brazil's President Luis Inacio Lula da Silva; and disputes between Argentina and Uruguay over human rights.
  - February 9, 2004, TW_TAM_835_ER_56
    The moderator of the episode was Cedric Robinson and the guests were Katia McClain and Gerard Pigeon. Discussed topics include a subway car explosion in Central Moscow; the cult of reluctant killers and the black widows of Chechnya; Haiti on the verge of civil war; the French–Ivorian clashes; and the Iraq War.
  - February 23, 2004, TW_TAM_835_ER_57
    The moderator of the episode was Cedric Robinson and the guests were Elizabeth Robinson and Gerard Pigeon. Discussed topics include the Haitian coup d'état and President Jean-Bertrand Aristide; the Iraq War; President George W. Bush preparing for his re-election campaign; transition to an independent Iraqi government; and hearings against Israel at the Hague about the West Bank wall.
  - March 1, 2004, TW_TAM_835_ER_58
    The moderator of the episode was Cedric Robinson and the guests were Katia McClain, Gerard Pigeon, and Elizabeth Robinson. Discussed topics include the Haitian coup d'état; the Caribbean Community and Common Market (CARICOM); the trial of President Slobodan Milošević at the Hague; the Czech Republic, and Slovakia becoming members of the European Union; and growing racism and prejudice against Roma communities in Eastern Europe.
  - March 8, 2004, TW_TAM_835_ER_59
    The moderator of the episode was Cedric Robinson and the guests were Ralph Ambruster-Sandoval and Elizabeth Robinson. Discussed topics include the Congressional International Relations Committee and Roger Noriega; pro-Aristide Haitian demonstration in Flatbush, Brooklyn; the Zimbabwe government's alleged seizure of an American cargo plane carrying suspected mercenaries; Ayatollah Sistani and the construction of a government/constitution in Iran; and the Salvadoran elections.
  - March 15, 2004, TW_TAM_835_ER_60
    The moderator of the episode was Elizabeth Robinson and the guests were Hector Javkin and Gerard Pigeon. Discussed topics include the Madrid train bombings, Spanish politics, U.S. intervention in Venezuelan politics, and anti-Iraq War demonstrations.
  - March 22, 2004, TW_TAM_835_ER_61
    The moderator of the episode was Elizabeth Robinson and the guests were Gary Colmenar and Katia McClain. Discussed topics include the South Korean and Filipino elections; NATO and UN occupation of Kosovo; failure of American attempts to reconstruct Iraq; and the construction of a wall to divide Israelis and Palestinians in the West Bank.
  - March 29, 2004, TW_TAM_835_ER_62
    The moderator of the episode was Cedric Robinson and the guests were Hector Javkin and Gerard Pigeon. Discussed topics include the history of human rights abuses in Argentina, the Rwandan genocide, the 1993 genocide in Burundi, and French involvement in both genocides.
  - April 5, 2004, TW_TAM_835_ER_63
    The moderator of the episode was Cedric Robinson and the guests were Ralph Ambruster-Sandoval and Katia McClain. Discussed topics include the 1994 Rwandan genocide; violence in Kosovo and Eastern Europe; and the Salvadorian elections.
  - April 12, 2004, TW_TAM_835_ER_64
    The moderator of the episode was Cedric Robinson and the guests were Phoebe Hirsch-Dubin (Mexico), Katia McClain, and Hector Javkin. Discussed topics include the 9/11 hearings; political relations between the U.S. and the Middle East; the North American Free Trade Agreement (NAFTA); and the Zapatista insurgency in Chiapas, Mexico.
  - April 26, 2004, TW_TAM_835_ER_65
    The moderator of the episode was Elizabeth Robinson and the guests were Hector Javkin and Gary Colmenar. Discussed topics include the release of Mordechai Vanunu from Shikma Prison; instability throughout the Middle East; the Iraq War; and the South Korean and Filipino elections.
  - May 3, 2004, TW_TAM_835_ER_66
    The moderator of the episode was Elizabeth Robinson and the guests were Katia McClain and Hector Javkin. Discussed topics include abuses by U.S. military personnel on Iraqi prisoners; Argentina's history of human rights violations and American involvement; the role of the Catholic church in Argentina; and changes in the European economic and political union.
  - May 10, 2004, TW_TAM_835_ER_67